Hey guys Shan this side welcome to
concept and coding and today in
microservices topic I'm going to cover
very important part is service discovery
right so we will cover both like
interview perceptive questions and also
we will see the implementation also how
we can set up the service discovery
servers and client and we'll see the
demo also okay so in microservices
service or component are created and
deleted dynamically we can know that
Right. So let's say our instances
itself, let's say we have our
microservices order
definitely in microservices one of the
advantage is that we can have as many
instances based on the traffic. But
these number keep on changing. If
traffic is more I can spawn more
instances. If traffic is less I can
reduce the number of instances. So
instances are created and deleted
dynamically.
We cannot hardcode the URL of a
particular instance. It's not scalable
and not feasible. So till now while we
seen rest template rest client f client
order service is making call to product
service and everywhere we have hardcoded
the URL. So it's okay for the testing
perspective but in production we never
hardcode these URLs right. So in above
example order service has hardcoded the
URL of the product service and it is
okay till we have only one instance of
product service. If you have only one
instance then it's okay you can hardcode
it. But in case if we have multiple
product service instance
right and which is very very possible
right let's say in this scenario so I
have instance one instance two instance
three all have different your IP address
and port number all has different IP
address and port number but if you have
hardcoded the URL your traffic will
always goes to one of the service only
goes to one of the service only Okay.
And it is also possible that a
particular instance can be removed. But
since you have hardcoded it, you you
will try to connect to an instance which
is removed. Then you will face
connectivity issue. Right? So there are
lot of challenges like first is single
point of failure. Single point of
failure is is hard-coded instance of
product service goes down order service
will not be able to communicate with
other instance. That's what I told like
if you have hardcoded it and I have
removed this instance then you won't be
able to communicate it. So it's a single
point of failure. No load balancing. So
even though I have three services since
you have hardcoded it every time the
traffic goes to this instance only even
though my these two other instances are
sitting idle. Okay. Tight coupling. So
because of hard-coded URL in the order
service, there is a tight coupleness
between order service and product
service. Now let's say that I have to
move the product service. Okay. And
maybe its IP and port address need to be
changed. Then you first have to update
the order service and then only you can
migrate your product service otherwise
it's not possible. Okay. So it brings a
tight coupling difficulty in testing
different environment might use
different URL which require frequent
changes in your config. So if you have
hardcoded it let's say now you are
testing on uh Dave then you need to
change this. If you're testing on stage
you are need to change this. Okay so
with different test environment uh
production QA Dave different URL and
then you have to keep on changing it if
you are doing a hardcoded.
So
one of the way we can overcome all this
limitation is our service discovery and
there are uh different uh tools like
Ureka or console.
Okay. So I am covering URA which is like
pretty much popular in the industry. So
but you can also go with the console
also the concept wise very much
similarity. Okay. So if you understand
one other you can easily grasp like
what's going on. So in service discovery
there are two parts server and client.
So server act as a phone book. Okay has
all the instances info of the registered
client like service name, instance ID,
IP, port number, health etc. So what is
that is server server is the one which
so this is the server server is the one
which actually keeps the details of all
the instances.
So instance one details instance two
details 3 4 5 all the different
instances it keeps the detail only thing
is only for the registered clients. So
client have to register them. So if we
have multiple clients client one, client
two, client three, so they have to
register with the server and then only
it would be maintaining the data of it.
We will see that how it is maintaining
how they can register it. But
just understand that for now that it is
a phone book only for the registered
client. So clients have to register and
after that once it is registered then
Eureka server you can consider as a
phone book like if you want a particular
details of a registered client you can
get all the info that for this is the
client these are the instances this is
the IP address port number status up and
down. So if this client has 10 instances
all the details you can get it.
Similarly, ura client most of the
popular two operation client does is
first register itself with the server
that let's say if you have a client what
you can do with the client first is
register itself with the server that hey
server maintain my instances and its
info. Okay. Another is discover an
instance. Let's say that if this client
one needs the detail of client two like
this client two has multiple instances.
Okay. And this client two is also
registered with the server means server
is maintaining these all instances info.
Now this client one need the details of
client two. What it will do is discovers
an instance. So it will ask the server
that hey I want to talk to client two.
Can you tell me the instances available?
So server now since it's a phone book,
it can return all the possible instances
of client 2 which are up.
Okay.
So now see this diagram. This is going
to be flow now. So now order service
first
get the list of a product service from
the ureka. If it has to invoke the
product service,
ureka server will return the product
service instances detail. If there are
10 instances of the product, it will
return all the 10 details which are up.
Okay. And after that it will order
service is the one which choose a
particular instance and then makes a
call.
Okay. So there is couple of things. This
is very simplistic
diagram. There are many things like
cache comes into the picture so that it
don't have to invoke the endpoint every
time. There are lot of things we will
see later but for now just understand
that order service doesn't hardcode it.
It will fetch the instances of the
details product service details from the
Ureka server. Ureka server return all
the instances detail of a product
service. Order service is the one which
choose a particular instance or you are
saying that it can do load balancing,
choose a particular instance and invoke
an endpoint.
Okay. So now let's set up each
application one by one. So let's set up
ureka server once. So I am creating a
new application through spring
initializer. Okay. So you can we have
already set up so many applications till
now. You can set up one uh simple
application dependency I have only put
web for now. So very very simple
application I have created. Now to make
it a ureka server what we have to do
first I am adding a dependency.
So this is the first step like I am
adding a spring cloud starter Netflix
ureka server dependency as ureka is
developed by Netflix which has been
integrated in spring cloud. Uh so this
is the dependency we have to add and for
the version which version I am using the
dependency management we have already
seen right in previously in fain client
also I have also mentioned that uh for
the spring cloud it's always better that
use dependency management uh to resolve
the version of it don't put direct
version here because in spring cloud if
if in future you have to add more
dependency
of spring cloud then those
different
let's say fing I am using also fin so
fing is like different cloud spring
cloud different library this is ureka
server is different library so they
should be
compatible to each other so you the
version which you are picking should be
compatible to each other so I don't want
to handle uh this version compatibility
I don't want to manually handle that. So
that's why dependency management helps
me in that or you can say that ease the
task for us. So we just tell what
dependency we want its version. This
will take care of it. Okay. So we have
added a ureka server
dependency in our pom.xml. So that's the
first thing. Second thing what we have
done is we have enabled the ureka
server. So we have put the
annotation at the rate enable ureka
server. So it tells spring boot to
create necessary beans which is required
for ureka server like ureka controller
dashboard etc. Okay. So till you don't
add this annotation the beans will not
be created which is required for ureka
server. So we have to tell the spring
boot that it's a ureka server
application. Treat it as a ureka server.
Okay. The third is
application.properties.
So the application name I have given the
port on which it's going to run. I have
given. Now these two are important. So I
told you what does the client do? Two
things.
The I have a client. This is a server.
Client does two things. One is register
itself and another is discover the
instance like hey give me the instance
discover fetch other instances so if you
are a server I don't want to do both
this thing so that's why register with
ureka false fetch registry false by
default these two are true so I told
that hey I don't have to since this is a
server I don't have to register it and
since this is a server I don't have to
fetch the registry also I don't have to
discover also okay so I have both made
the false
so these three things I have done and
what's the port number I have configured
8761 so if I put started the application
and put local host 8761 this is the
dashboard you're going to see so this
dashboard would be up so currently no
application is registered
No instances registered.
So now let's set up a Ureka client
application. Now so Ureka server is
clear, right? How we can enable it?
Ureka server, Ureka client application.
So now let's say that order service I
have we have different microservices
like order service, product service and
let's say that first they have to
register themselves to the Ureka server.
How they can register it? Okay. So now
let's say that product service the first
thing first we have to add a dependency.
So here we are adding a dependency of a
client ureka client spring cloud starter
Netflix ureka client in the server we
have added a dependency of the server
one
ureka server and here we are adding a
dependency of ureka client and similarly
its version I am living to this
dependency management.
Okay. Second thing
application.properties.
So I have set a port number, application
name that it's a product service which I
want to show into the dashboard also.
Right now this three part very
important.
First thing is client register with
ureka. Do you want to register this
application with ureka? True. You don't
even have to add it. By default these
are true. But just for showing purpose
that we these two things are important
for the client. If you don't write these
two then also it will work because by
default these two are true only. Do you
want to fetch the registry? True. So
let's say that in your case if your
scenario is that only you want to
register you don't want to fetch you can
make it false one also. Or you only want
to fetch you don't want to register
yourself then you can make this false.
Okay. So you can play with this uh
values but understand what's the purpose
of this two configs
and this one this one is also important
that ureka client service URL default
zone so here we have to provide the URL
where this client will talk with this
ureka okay so currently this ureka
server is running on port number 8761 on
the local host okay and that / ureka
this is the default endpoint
Okay.
So this is we have to put into this
config ureka client service url dot
default zone.
This is very important because without
this your client won't be able to talk
with the ureka server. So this is your
server URL.
Okay. So I started the product service.
Now see the dashboard. Once you started
the product service.
Okay. You will see the same dashboard
you will see product service. So product
this is the service name we have given
right in small. So here it shows capital
letter product service and
the
address complete address like what is
the instance ID port number URL status
up or not.
Okay. So our client is now registered
with the product. Similarly for order
service also we can do the same thing in
the order service also you have to put
the dependency in pom
application.properties properties give
it a order - service you need to tell
the server uh ureka server URL and you
can make it true if you want both the
capability register it and the fetching
both it and once you refresh it once you
start the product order service will
also come
okay
so now our server is set up and client
is also set up means client application
also registered themsel
now let's see How order service can
invoke product service? Now order
service has to invoke the product
service like now we can do. So this is
the previous without service discovery.
Earlier let's say we were using rest
template. So we were creating a rest
template object. After that we were
invoking get for object if you remember
if you can recall and then we'll give
the URL. We hardcoded URL.
This is the hardcoded URL of the product
service. Okay. Specifically we were
mentioning the URL. Okay. Now with
service discovery what we have to do is
if you are using a rest template then
there is something called discovery
client. It is present into spring
framework
cloudclient.discocovery.discocovery
client.
Okay. So this discovery client we have
to first fetch an instance discovery.
You have to discovery the instances. So
get an instance of this service product
service. So remember the name should be
given properly which other application
has set up in their application.name
because the same name goes here into the
ureka server also. Okay. So you are
using a discovery client
object to fetch the instances of a
particular service. Now what would
happen is you will get a list of
instances. You get a list of instances
and this service instance contain lot of
information like URL, port number, the
URI, uh name, lot more information. So
but consider this that in the rest
template
in the rest template
once we get a list of instances let's
say for product service there could be
10 instances there could be 100
instances
so we have to choose a particular
instance you have to manually do the
load balancing so for now I am just
doing get zero no matter how many
instances do me the get zero this is
just an example but instead here load
balancer logic should be present either
round robin choose or whatever the
logic. So load balancing logic we have
to add it in the rest template or either
you have to integrate with spring cloud
load balancer
load balancer if you don't want to write
your own logic otherwise you have to
pick a particular instance and once you
get the instance use that URI here so
now here if you see that I have not
hardcoded it okay so I'm getting a list
of instances I am picking picking one of
the instance based on my logic load
balancing logic and whatever the
instance I have picked I am using that
and invoking the API.
Okay. So this is just a relative path
the host and port number is coming from
this.
So with rest template load balancing
logic need to be handled. But let's say
if you're using faint client or rest
client also the mostly the same behavior
with faint client load balancing is
handled automatically by the framework
itself. Now when you get a multiple
instance and framework has to choose
one. So load balancing is handled
automatically. So we have to add a load
balancing dependency also if you are
using faint client or rest client
because now framework has to pick a
particular instance. Okay. So now
framework is doing certain task for us
and if framework has to choose it
chooses via load balancing. Okay. So
whenever we use fang client plus service
discovery then we have to add a load
balancer dependency also
because it is load balancing is handled
automatically by the framework. So
earlier without service discovery what
we were doing is add the red fing client
I think you can recall this we we have
discussed in depth and we provide the
URL like the host and port number which
we were putting into
application.properties properties right
so we are providing some URL we are in
our application in
application.properties properties or
here itself. Now with service discovery
we don't need this only name with the
name itself whatever the name we have
provided for the application right which
we want to talk like let's say product
service
then with this name itself the framework
will you internally use discovery client
fetch the instance use the load balancer
pick a particular instance and invoke it
all by the framework now we don't have
to hardcode the URL
All we just have to give the name which
is used in the service discovery.
Okay.
So this look pretty simple right? Uh
setting up a service discovery but in
interview there are certain questions
comes it. So as a curious engineer the
few things which comes to your mind is
that how does ureka server know whether
a client is up or down?
where and how the data is stored in the
ureka server. What if ureka server
itself goes down? Is it a single point
of failure or not?
Now earlier order service is directly
calling product service. Now it is
making like order service is calling
urea server and then after that urea
server is giving the list and then order
service is making a call to product
service. So it's like a first hop second
hop. So now does it cause a latency
issue?
Okay. So we will see all this answer
like uh which is very important from the
interview perspective and also our
understanding also.
So first thing is how does Ureka server
knows whether a client is up or not. So
Ureka server know by two way. First is
client dregistration request. Another is
through client heartbeat.
Let's say that first
when client application is gracefully
shut down then ureka client send a dre
registration request to ureka server it
marked the client status as down okay so
now let's say that
currently product service is up okay now
I shut down this product service
application from the ID I shut down this
application so if you see the log
You will see that hey it will call
unregistering application with Ureka
with status down. It is calling the
Ureka server with the status down and
after that and if you check the server
ureka server logs it received it
registered instance this with the status
down and then it updated the status with
down for this one.
Okay. So one is through if gracefully
things happening then dregistration call
happen from client to server and with
that ureka server know that client is
down but now let's say assume that your
client got shut down but without any
without sending any dregistration
request maybe because of network issue
or something then how it will know it
will know through heartbeat
every client periodically sends
heartbeat to the Ureka server.
Okay. So, Ureka server wait for the
heartbeat from the client for a
particular interval. We can we can
configure this interval. I will show
you. Okay. So, Ureka server wait for the
heartbeat from client for a particular
interval. If no heartbeat receive within
that time interval, it remove the client
instance itself. It consider it dead.
So, consider this client
application.properties.
Okay. Let's say product service. So
these things we have set the port
number, application name, the Ureka
server URL and registry discovery. We
have already set this. Now concentrate
on this two new config. The first is
ureka.instance
dot least renewable interval. So least
renewable in interval in second means
that after this much seconds client will
set the new heartbeat to the server.
So I said 60 means after 60 seconds the
ureka client will send the heartbeat to
the server. If you don't set it by
default is 30 second.
Then another config is ureka.instance of
lease expiration duration in second.
Lease expiration. This is like telling
server to wait only this much time for
the heartbeat. After that you can remove
it from the list. default is 90 second.
So this means that client is telling to
the server that hey this is the maximum
time you can wait for my heartbeat. If
you don't get the heartbeat within this
time you can consider me as like
unavailable.
So in this example generally this time
is greater than this time but for this
example only I have taken it very less.
So after 60 seconds the client will send
the heartbeat to the server
but server will wait only for 5 seconds.
Okay. So it will mark it as dead. We
will see that and in this ureka server
application.properties what we have to
do is we have seen this config already.
Now these two config we have to set.
First is enable ureka.server enable
selfpreservation false. This by default
this is true. We have to make it false
because we need to allow server to
remove the instance if heartbeat is not
received. So if it is generally true
right so generally even though the
heartbeat is not received the server do
not remove it.
Okay. So
if you make it false then means we are
allowing the server. Hey if heartbeat is
missed feel free to remove it. Okay. And
the second is that eviction interval
timer. So sometime what happen is like
even the
uh even the client is down even the
client is down
but server has to run like server check
for the dead instances. Okay. Whatever
the instances are configured it has to
look a is this dead or not? If it is
dead remove it remove it from the list.
Remove it from the list. So we have to
check the eviction interval means how
often server check for dead instances
even the client is dead it's okay
so it and we have also tell that remove
it but it does it has to run through an
interval right it can't just like every
time it keep on running uh that I have
to remove it so we have I have set a
6cond after 6 second just look if you
see any dead instance
remove it. If you see any instance for
which heartbeat is missing, remove it
from the list.
So this is the client configuration.
This is the server configuration. Now
here if you see earlier
product service is up. Okay. And what is
the configuration? I have set heartbeat
uh which is I think a lease renewable
time I set is uh 60 seconds
and lease expiry
I think le expiry right lease expiration
duration I have set is 5 second means
after 60 seconds product service will
send the heartbeat but server will wait
only for 5 Okay. So after 5 seconds if
you see the application is removed from
the dashboard
from the registry itself.
Okay.
Because of this configuration
you can test this also right like here I
my application is running. Okay. So we
can check this like let me stop it uh
once. So ureka server self preservation
is false.
Interval 6 seconds I have set up and in
the product service
heartbeat will send for 60 and
expiration let me allow for five just
for testing purpose so that uh we can
check so let me start the urea server
for now
and let me start the product service
and then let's see
refresh it so currently product services
there up let's wait for 5 second 1 2 3 4
5 6 it's gone.
Okay.
So we can you can uh do testing and
these things will get clarified. Okay.
So we know the answer for this one,
right? How ureka server know whether a
client is up or down?
The second is how does ureka server
stores the data? Ureka server only store
data in memory. There is no uh you can
say that DB persistence. No, only in
memory. It creates a map
string, lease uh
instance info. Okay. So here if you see
that the key is your app name/ instance
ID. So this is generally your key. what
is the app name and what is the
particular instance ID
IP port number and the particular
service.
Okay, this totally generate a unique
instance
unique instance because IP is different
port number IP port number and the
product app name. This makes a unique
instance. So this is your key and in the
value you have the value of like app
name, IP address, host name, port,
whether this is up or down, when it was
last renewed, lease duration, etc.
Okay,
so this is how Ureka server stores the
data. But there is remember there is no
DB persistence. It's all in memory.
Now what if Ureka server goes down
itself? Is it a single point of failure?
So now let's say we know that URA server
is storing the data in memory. So I have
this map. I have this map in memory.
Right?
Uka server. Now if this server goes down
this all this infos goes away with it.
Now if order service has to call the
product service it will call this
server. Will it be available? No. It's
gone. It's down.
So is it URA server is bringing a single
point of failure in our application? No.
So if you are using a single URA server
then yes. But generally
three nodes are used. Okay. It is used
in a ureka server cluster. We create a
URA server cluster. So three servers are
running into different machine or
container with different IP and port
number. Okay. So on three different
machine three ureka servers are running.
Okay. And here each server is a client
two. This is very important. So now
let's say that you have a cluster
of three ureka server. Server one server
2 server 3. Uka server 1 2 3. Now this
server has to register itself to both
this server. First it has to register
right. Second it also has to take
whatever the data present into S2. So it
has to discover also.
Okay. So means this server is also now
becomes a client.
So the same thing each server is a
client two as they have to register
themsel fetch the registry replicate the
changes. So now let's say that your
three servers which are running into
three different
uh machines. So configuration for them
would be like let's say for server one
would be
application name port number your host
name instance like on which uh port
number it is running IP address okay now
here if you see even for the server I am
registering ureka doclient.registered
with ureka true yes I want to register
it also I am making it true ureka.client
client do.fet registry true yes I want
to fetch the details also so even though
it is a server I am treating it as a
client also okay so it's a client of
whom so for its server would be these
two
server ureka server which is running on
this one second ureka ureka 2 server and
the ureka server which is running on
8763 this one so for this so this is a
client for these two. So it registered
itself with these two servers.
Similarly, server two is also a client
of
server two now is a client of this and
this.
Okay. Similarly, server 3 is a client of
one and two server.
Okay. And in the client
application.properties, properties
earlier we were putting the default zone
right we can say that hey we can put all
three servers here so 1 2 3
okay that's all we have to do so here
internally the ureka server internally
whenever any let's say this is server
one server 2 server three okay they have
their
maps all sync
any new entry happen here let's say
instance one certain detail it will
update the detail here so it's eventual
consistency it's not like always you
will get like so let's say that the data
present into server one instance detail
so eventually it will also be present
into s_ub_2 and eventually it will also
be present into s3 okay but there is no
guarantee that your client
Now your client can request to anybody.
Let's say that if your ureka server one
is down, it can call ureka server 2
also. So there is no guarantee that the
instance one detail which is pres
present in s1 is properly sync up in
s_ub_2. Eventually it will but there is
no guarantee that let's say if request
goes into s_ub_2 you will get the data.
You might not not but if you retry you
might
okay because they keep on syncing up the
data but there could be some delay and
because of that if your request goes to
server one
you might see the data if it goes to
server two you might not. So service
discovery is a provide eventual
consistency.
Okay. So your client is now
configured this three service discovery
URLs.
So if one server is down it will not
impact the client availability now. So
there is no single point of failure.
Can it cause a latency issue like
earlier we were making a direct call
from order service to product service.
Now first uh I have to invoke ureka
server and then make the actual call.
No, Eureka server does not get called
for every request. At application
startup itself, the client let's say
order service need to call to product
service. So at CL application startup
itself, it fetch the registry. We have
set this right uh fetch the registry. So
it will fetch everything from Ureka
server at the time of application
startup and it will put into its cache
locally. Order service put into it cache
locally.
Now all the future call it will use this
local copy only to find the instance. It
will not call Ureka server
and we can control this config like
after how after how much seconds client
will refresh it cache copy because now
you have put this data into the cache.
Okay. So
the original data which is present into
the server it might get changed certain
instances from up changed to down or it
got removed itself totally or new got
added. How this cache copy get updated.
So we can configure this
ureka.client.registry registry fetch
interval second whatever the second you
will put after that much seconds it will
update its cache copy
okay so this is the client configuration
and what if the local cache is stale can
this lead to calling a dead instance
possible right let's say that here
instance one was marked as down so order
service
product service and let's say this is
server and Here instance one is up and
during application startup it maintain
the copy instance one up but later on
let's say that it has make it down
instance one is down but
let's say that this time is not yet
happened it has not refreshed its copy
yet you have given such a big time
interval let's say I have given it as
something let's say that
something thousand. So I have given very
big interval like or let's say 10,000
something like
so it hasn't updated its copy cache
copy. So it might got a stale. So even
though this
order service see that hey this instance
one is up it will try to call but
actually it's down.
Okay. So you have to be very careful
with this timing.
If you keep it very less, if you keep it
let's say this is order service, this is
your ureka server. If you keep this
let's say 1 second. So after 1 second,
it will always make a call and keep on
doing refresh refresh refresh refresh.
Okay, that is also not good. If you keep
it too large then you might get a stale
data here and it might possible that you
are in your cache copy it's showing up
but actually it's down and when you try
to call it ultimately fail. So it's a
tradeoff. So you have to have a proper
this number should come up with a proper
that this cache copy should be updated
in how much time so that you have always
have the latest
data also you don't keep on refreshing
it as many as possible like we don't
want that we want as minimum as possible
refresh but still the data as fresh
okay so do practice with your hand like
uh but this is very very important topic
it's widely used in the industry but I
hope we can if you have any further
doubt we can further discuss into the
comment section but I hope uh it clarify
lot of your doubts and it will give you
a path forward like more you can jump
into this topic like console you can
further go into that one okay guys thank
you bye